Guide to the Nathaniel Pendleton Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Nathaniel Pendleton Family papers
1716-1853
MS 392
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.75
(1 box, 1 folio)
Correspondence and legal and financial papers reflecting Pendleton's service in the Revolutionary Army as aide-de-camp to General Nathanael Greene, and his close connection with Alexander Hamilton. The correspondence includes letters from Samuel Finley, Mrs. Nathanael Greene, Alexander von Humboldt and Otho Holland Williams. Legal and financial papers as well as correspondence of Alexander Hamilton are also included since Pendleton was executor of his estate. Also included are legal documents of the Bard family and papers of other members of the Pendleton family, among them Edmund H. Pendleton and Philip C. Pendleton. Other documents in the papers relate to Indian lands in Georgia (1788) and a summary of a treaty between the King of Spain and the Creek, Choctaw, Chickasaw and Cherokee Indians, dated 1793.
Pendleton, Nathaniel, 1756-1821
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. F. C. Rogers, 1953.
Scope and Contents
This is an exceedingly interesting group of papers, both in authorship and in content. Among the Nathaniel Pendleton papers are nine letters from Pendleton to General Otho Holland Williams and autograph drafts of letters to James Monroe, Justice Story, and George Washington; Pendleton's certificate of admission to the Supreme Court of New York is also present. There are letters to Pendleton from Samuel Finley, Nathanael Greene, John Laurance, R.S. Livingston, Catharine (Littlefield) Greene Miller, Edmund Pendleton (1721-1803), Timothy Pickering, and Otho Holland Williams. One letter is labelled Edmund Randolph but apparently written by someone else.
Papers and letters to, by, or relating to Alexander Hamilton and his estate include two bills and a bond to Louis LeGuen and a mortgage deed to the latter's trustees, all by Hamilton; letters to Hamilton from John Laurance, Louis LeGuen, William Rufus Putnam, Philip John Schuyler; one share in the "Company for Promoting the Cultivation of Vines"; a bill of exchange endorsed by Hamilton; two lists of land purchases apparently with John Barker Church, who was one of Hamilton's executors; letters and other papers dealing with Hamilton's estate; one letter from his wife to an unnamed person, and one paper by her.
Other Pendletons are also represented in the collection. Of Edmund Henry Pendleton there is a commission as judge in Dutchess County and a petition in a bill of information in chancery; of Philip Clayton Pendleton, Sr., one ALS; of Ann (Pendleton) Pierce, a will; and of Henry Pendleton (1750-1788), an inventory of his estate. Other letters and papers include the will of John Bard, Jr.; the signature of George Clarke (1676-1760) on a list of recognizances; an ALS from Baron Humboldt to Monsieur Pendleton; resolutions of Congress respecting cession of Indian lands in Georgia; a pew list of St. James Episcopal Church in Hyde Park; an ALS from Moses White to John Barker Church; a deed from Trinity Episcopal Church, New York, to Andrew Morris, and one from John Morrin Scott to Dr. John Bard; the marriage bond of Frederick H. Cossitt and Catharine Andrus; and an order concerning a bond of John Graham.
Biographical / Historical
Nathaniel Pendleton (1756-1821) was born in Culpepper County, Virginia, and died in Hyde Park, New York. He served in the Revolutionary forces for eight years and five months and was in the last part aide-de-camp to General Nathanael Greene. An original member of the Society of the Cincinnati in South Carolina, Virginia, Georgia, and New York, he was also a member of the Constitutional Convention in 1788. He acted as Alexander Hamilton's second in his duel with Aaron Burr, and was one of the executors of Hamilton's estate. He became a prominent jurist. He married Susan Bard, daughter of John Bard, a friend of Benjamin Franklin.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Families; Indians of North America -- Treaties; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Wills; Lawyers; Soldiers; Finley, Samuel, 1752-1829; Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859; Laurance, John, 1750-1810; Le Guen, Louis; Livingston, Richard, 1744-1786; Miller, Catherine Littlefield Greene, 1755-1814; Pendleton, Edmund, 1721-1803; Pendleton, Henry, 1750-1788; Pendleton, Nathaniel, 1756-1821; Pendleton, Philip C., 1799-1863; Putnam, William Rufus, b. 1771; Schuyler, Philip John, 1733-1804; Williams, Otho Holland, 1747-1794; Baird family; Pendleton family
- Inventory, 1716-1853
  - Bard family
    - John Bard: will, 1800 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ann [(Bard)?] Pierce: estate papers, 1833, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alexander Hamilton, 1757-1804
    - Incoming letters
      - John Laurance, 1797 June 3, 17; 1798 December 28 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Louis LeGuen, 1803 September 30; 1804 July 12 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - William Rufus Putnam, 1803 January 17 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Philip John Schuyler, 1803 December 10 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Legal and financial papers, 1801-1808 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Edmund H. Pendleton, 1786-1862
    - Pew list for St. James' Church, Hyde Park, N.Y., 1815 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Certificate of appointment as First Judge of Dutchess County, N.Y., 1830 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Nathaniel Pendleton, 1756-1821
    - Incoming letters
      - Samuel Finley, 1810 February 22; 1812 March 10 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Nathanael Greene, 1789 November 22 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Alexander von Humboldt, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - John Laurance, 1807 August 29 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - R. S. Livingston, 1815 February 27 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Catherine (Littlefield) Greene Miller, 1790 May 3, July 27; 1792 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Edmund Pendleton (1721-1803), 1787 October 10; 1788 November 25; 1794 February 3 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Henry Pendleton, 1782 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Timothy Pickering, 1810 January 6 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Otho Holland Williams, 1782 November 10 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Unidentified (labelled "Edmund Randolph," but written by someone else), Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - ALS (draft) to James Monroe, 1817 April 7 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - ALS (draft) to Joseph Story, 1817 June 22 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - AL (draft) to George Washington, 1789 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 9 ALS to Otho Holland Williams, 1782-1784 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Inventory of Henry Pendleton's personal estate (copy), 1790 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Endorsement of an order concerning a bond of John Graham, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Certificate of admission to the New York State Supreme Court, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Philip C. Pendleton
    - ALS to Nathaniel G. Pendleton, 1841 December 10 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "List of Recognizances for Excise made good to the Crown by Peter Fauconnier.. .," signed by George Clarke, 1716/17 March 19 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Resolutions of Congress respecting the cession of Indian lands in Georgia, 1788 July 15 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "Heads of a Treaty between the King of Spain and the Creek, Choctaw, Chickasaw, and Cherokee Indians, Dated at Walnut Hills October 28th, 1793. Containing 19 Articles", Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Certificate that Cromwell Catlin has completed a bridge across the North River, signed by William Butler, 1828 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Certificate of marriage between Frederick H. Cossitt and Catharine Andrus, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Account of a conversation with Mr. Beekman in the Ladies' Parlor, Congress Hall, Albany, about the creation of a park, [post-1853] (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Notes on the Socinians, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Oversize
    - Deed from John Morin Scott to John Bard, 1761 (Box 2)
    - Deed from Trinity Church, New York City, to Andrew Morris, 1787 (Box 2)
    - Indenture between Edmund H. Pendleton and the trustees of Frances Maria (Jones) Pendleton, 1811 (Box 2)
    - Unidentified account naming Alexander Hamilton among others, Undated (Box 2)